<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-11-21T21:09:37-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Blogajandro</title><subtitle>Thinking in public.</subtitle><author><name>Alejandro Londono</name><email>alejandro [at] londonos [dot] com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Calliope</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fiction/shortstories/2021/08/11/calliope.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Calliope" /><published>2021-08-11T19:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-11T19:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fiction/shortstories/2021/08/11/calliope</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fiction/shortstories/2021/08/11/calliope.html">&lt;p&gt;Cali wandered through the small store away from her father. Vintage hand me downs littered the space, discarded trash to anyone passing by who might fleetingly glance, but hidden treasures to those who knew what to look for. Cali’s father stayed behind admiring old lamps and chests and wardrobes, leaving her free to venture deeper into the back. She crossed a doorway parted by curtains and entered a room lined with bookshelves reaching high into a void. Dim lights hung from a ceiling hidden by height and lingering dust. On the shelves, books written by the great characters of history hugged others from nobodies that no one had ever bothered to remember, and never would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cali explored the labyrinthine shelves, scanning the titles. Some stared at her in English, while others greeted her in French, Spanish, Arabic, Hebrew, Sanskrit. A few wore tongues no other man or woman alive would recognize, save the old clerk that managed the bookstore. The same clerk who now appeared behind the girl, silently, like a shadow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Can I help you, child?” he asked, “Is there any book in particular you search for?”, a timbre in his voice pierced the air only to break on paper dense shelves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“N-no sir. I’m just looking sir. My father is up front and I came to look at the books. I like stories… Do you have any books with a good story?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ah, a good story…? Perhaps. Come with me child.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clerk turned swiftly on his heels and floated down the aisle with a smooth gait that seemed to never touch the floor. At the end of the path he took a sharp turn and disappeared. The girl scampered behind him trying to keep up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Cali caught up to the clerk, he stood at the very back of the store behind a wooden desk flooded with disorganized heaps of books and paper sheets. Seeing her approach, he pulled out an ancient, yet sturdy, leather bound book. This book had clearly passed through hundreds, if not thousands, of hands, but had been made with such skill and handled with such care that the original binding still held like on its first day of print.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old man lugged the book up from under his desk and dropped it on the wood with a thud. Dust blew into the air clouding the pair’s vision. The clerk placed his hand on the cover and spoke,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Here child. The stories in this text are many. Feel free to stay and read as long as you like. I have some work to attend to in the front, but will return to bring you back to your father once he beckons for you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cali pulled a stool up to the desk and clambered onto it. She examined the book cover but saw no title. No author. No text whatsoever. Just a leather jacket wrapping a bound stack of papers. She turned to the first page expecting to see the missing information, but it remained absent, the book plunged its reader straight into the story from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What’s the name of this book… ?” Cali asked, looking up to address the clerk. But he had gone. She turned around, searching down the book shelf alleys for him, but only empty aisles greeted her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shifting back in her seat, Cali turned to the text and began to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fantastical stories greeted her. Of pirates with ships covered in moss that roamed swamps in a far away land, patrolling for unlucky merchants travelling between kingdoms.  Of thieves who cloaked themselves with shadows, masterfully bending light to hide themselves from their victims until a knife against their throat emptied their pockets. She read stories of machiavellian women who bent men to their will, and ruled fierce, expanding empires, paired with tales of a maiden who travelled through the centuries curing lepers, restoring burn victims, and remitting cancer patients. She read of great beasts that once roamed the earth hunting humans for sport. She read of the beginning of a universe much like ours, and how everything in it came to be. She met the characters of this universe and witnessed the great and terrible things they did. She embarked on adventures with heroes who left their homes to confront the unknown; Who fell and stumbled, only to rise again and learn from their failures. Heroes who bettered themselves and overcame evil, returning home having changed the world and the world having changed them. She read and read and read, for what felt to her like hours, stories she had never heard before and never would again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And once Cali had had her fill of stories, she closed the book and looked up from reading. There stood the clerk again at the other side of the desk, old kind eyes nested in a smile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How were the stories, child?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh they were amazing! I’ve never read stories this wonderful in my life, who wrote them?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hmm… this is a book unlike any you have ever read. And unlike any you ever will. It holds infinite stories that have never appeared before today for no one has ever written them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What do you mean no one has written these stories? They’re right here. Someone must have written them down.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clerk smiled. “Tell me child, which was your favorite of the stories?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh it’s hard to pick, they were all so good!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What was the last one you read? The one you just finished.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh that one was so good. It was about… well there was this… uh… it was… um…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t remember.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And you never will. But you will remember how they made you feel, and you will recognize that same magic in future stories you read. The stories here, they do not exist. But perhaps another story of similar quality will, one day. Perhaps you will write it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah! I’ll write my stories down so that no one will forget them like I did just now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clerk smiled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Come along now child, your father is waiting for you in the front.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cali jumped off the stool and followed the clerk back to the entrance where she’d left her father. Upon seeing him, she ran up  and hooked her hand to his. The pair left the store, and the whole journey home Cali made up stories and told them to her father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they were quite magical stories at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thanks to Ross Hardin, Hannah Gooden, and Sean Valley for reading drafts of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Alejandro Londono</name></author><category term="fiction" /><category term="shortstories" /><summary type="html">Cali wandered through the small store away from her father. Vintage hand me downs littered the space, discarded trash to anyone passing by who might fleetingly glance, but hidden treasures to those who knew what to look for. Cali’s father stayed behind admiring old lamps and chests and wardrobes, leaving her free to venture deeper into the back. She crossed a doorway parted by curtains and entered a room lined with bookshelves reaching high into a void. Dim lights hung from a ceiling hidden by height and lingering dust. On the shelves, books written by the great characters of history hugged others from nobodies that no one had ever bothered to remember, and never would.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How does Bitcoin Fit Into the Larger Framework of History?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cryptocurrency/blogposts/2021/04/06/btc-place-history.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How does Bitcoin Fit Into the Larger Framework of History?" /><published>2021-04-06T12:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-04-06T12:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cryptocurrency/blogposts/2021/04/06/btc-place-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cryptocurrency/blogposts/2021/04/06/btc-place-history.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bitcoin and cryptocurrency will replace fiat currency as the dominant form of transactional capital on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to be the manifest destiny of every crypto-evangelist I have ever encountered, online or in real life. And I don’t know if it’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to clarify. I don’t mean that as in “I doubt that it’s true”, as it sometimes implies. I mean that I literally don’t know. I don’t think anyone really does, because it hasn’t happened. &lt;em&gt;Yet&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re watching it play out, in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the statement compels me. It intrigues me. It’s exciting. And in the process of exploring it, I started breaking it down further, trying to find the fundamental question that drives it. I arrived at the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How does decentralized power supersede centralized power?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This felt fundamental. First principled. So I set out to answer it and tie it back to the world of cryptocurrency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My answer comes in the form of a framework for how centralization and decentralization manifest in society. This framework will enable us to compare the properties of different systems in history against each other and against cryptocurrency. It should help us show how one system replaces another, and perhaps, allow us to examine our opening statement through a new lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this framework we begin with two axes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1) Decentralization &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Centralization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(2) Disorganized &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Organized&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Axis (1) indicates the extent of centralization or decentralization of power in a system. On one end of this axis we see low centralization (high decentralization) and on the other high centralization (low decentralization).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we take a look at the extreme end of the low centralization side we find, for example, anarchy. Idealized &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/anarchism/#AnarHistPoliPhil&quot;&gt;anarchy&lt;/a&gt; is stateless with no hierarchy; Constituents, theoretically, distribute power evenly and independently between each other. No governing body or person holds any greater power than another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another decentralization example, a little further up the axis, is pure, idealized, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/direct-democracy&quot;&gt;direct democracy&lt;/a&gt;. Here, a state does exist, but the power to govern it is again distributed throughout the populace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the opposite extreme of axis (1) we see high centralization of power. Authoritarian dictatorships appear on this extremity, where a single entity holds a high amount of power, and all others retain no power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shifting focus, Axis (2) represents the degree of organization involved in producing a given result. High organization indicates that all parties participating in the system premeditated the outcome.  This means a high degree of planning and collective agreement goes into realizing a result. In contrast, low organization sees results happen organically, non-consensually, or without collective planning and agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Axis (2) becomes clearer when paired with axis (1), as we see below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/centralization_organization_matrix.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image above produces four quadrants &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#footnoteone&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#footnotetwo&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organized x Centralization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disorganized x Decentralization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disorganized x Centralization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organized x Decentralization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the top right corner we see &lt;strong&gt;organized centralization&lt;/strong&gt;. This occurs when centralization of power is the intended result of a collective body, and all (or at least most) parties in the system agree to increase the power of some central entity. A prime example of this quadrant appears in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/dictator-Roman-official&quot;&gt;the dictators of the Roman Republic&lt;/a&gt; to whom, during times of great crisis, and for a limited time, the Roman Senate granted great authoritarian power. Here, we immediately see power centralizing when the individual named as dictator is granted authority comparable to the rest of the senate. Along the other dimension, the aspect of high organization comes from the &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt; to centralize power.  The process through which the power centralized was premeditated, consented to, and encouraged by the members of Roman society at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving diagonally to the bottom left quadrant takes us into the territory of &lt;strong&gt;disorganized decentralization&lt;/strong&gt;. This arrangement occurs when power is distributed about many factions, but not through a premeditated system. Instead it distributes by chance or, often, collapse. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ancient.eu/article/835/fall-of-the-western-roman-empire/&quot;&gt;fall of the Western Roman Empire&lt;/a&gt; to Germanic tribes exemplifies this. Though many factors played a role in the fall of the empire, and the decline happened over a long period of time, the eventual collapse saw power that once centralized around the emperor of Rome disperse among the Visigoths, Lombards, Saxons, Burgundians, Angles, and other Germanic tribes. The fall of Rome, however, was not an organized event. The forces that decentralized its power did not result from collusion between the Romans and the Barbarians to re-distribute power among the continent’s different Germanic factions. It came, instead, from structural failure in the empire, and opportunistic, but disorganized, sackings of the Roman territories by the Germanic groups. Ergo disorganized decentralization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we shift our attention to the bottom right corner, we find &lt;strong&gt;disorganized centralization&lt;/strong&gt; which results from an increase in centralized power &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; a collective  imperative to concentrate it. The most common instance of this occurs after violent, forceful unification of territories under a single monarch. Continuing  our previous examples, after the Western Roman Empire fell, and Europe descended into a divided Middle Ages, it found itself in a period of warring states between the barbarian tribes until Frankish unification occurred under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/history-of-Europe/The-Frankish-ascendancy#ref993860&quot;&gt;Merovingian and Carolingian&lt;/a&gt; dynasties, forming the Holy Roman Empire. The European continent  did not unify under a single monarch due to organized collusion between all the existing tribes. Rather, Charlemagne’s conquering of neighboring tribes, and  placing them under his rule led to the creation of the Holy Roman Emperor. During this period, power forcefully transitioned from a decentralized warring state to a centralized one under a single ruler, or centralization in a disorganized fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our final quadrant, in the top right, &lt;strong&gt;Organized decentralization&lt;/strong&gt;, emerges when a collective party organizes and consents to taking what might have been centralized power and distributing it among a larger faction. When the American founding fathers designed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/federalism&quot;&gt;federalist&lt;/a&gt; system that distributed much of the federal government’s power out to the states, they enacted organized decentralization. The distribution of that power was premeditated and agreed upon by all members of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The differentiating detail between organized and disorganized decentralization is the degree of premeditation. Organized decentralization plans on decentralizing before the distribution of power occurs. It’s intentional. Disorganized decentralization is more accidental or unintentional, power disperses, often because some central entity seemingly loses their hold on it and it spills out (though it can also manifest in other ways).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cryptocurrency is the latest implementation of &lt;em&gt;organized&lt;/em&gt; decentralization. A collective has decided to attribute financial value to a series of digital hashes, and the power to regulate this new currency has been distributed to all the participants. No central authority controls this new digital money, and that is by design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crypto is perhaps the purest form of decentralization of power human society has ever achieved. Extreme decentralization has happened before,  it often followed systemic collapse, but due to the degree of &lt;em&gt;disorganization&lt;/em&gt;, this decentralized power proved largely unstable and eventually re-centralized. Organized decentralization has likewise appeared before, but never at such a high degree of distribution and scale. Federalism decentralized power away from the federal government, but not completely, retaining strong powers in the central government and within the government of each state. By contrast, Cryptocurrency has increased the degree of decentralization by distributing power to the individual level. Pure democracy has had its trial runs before, but never seen success at scale, reaching its participant limit in the low thousands. Crypto, on the other hand, has scaled, with millions of people participating around the world simultaneously. This is no accident. With the internet, our level of technological advancement finally allows for mass organization in a way that has never been possible before. In turn, our societal ability to decentralize increased, now capable of distributing powers previously un-distributable. This is why Cryptocurrency has succeeded so far, and will be a fundamental reason for its continued success, if it does indeed continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As stated earlier, I don’t know whether cryptocurrency will effectively replace fiat, but it seems to have the right qualities of organization and decentralization to enable its success, and though the future remains unclear, it is damn exciting to see it push the boundaries of what we can achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a name=&quot;footnoteone&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;] The quadrants shown seem to discretize the model, but it should be noted that it can also be interpreted as a set of continuous axes creating a continuous plane. If the centralization or organization of a system can somehow be quantified, then points or vectors  would appear on this plane and enable comparison across and within quadrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a name=&quot;footnotetwo&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;] A friend suggested that I include more examples of technology and where the systems they enable fall on the centralization-organization matrix.  I have detailed some here, but it may be beneficial to wait until finishing the main body of this post before reading this footnote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets: Disorganized Decentralization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be argued that markets are not really a technology, as technology implies invention, and are instead a naturally emergent system of human behavior.  However, as they are emergent from &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt; behavior they might be categorized as an unintentional human invention. Regardless, they are a powerful and important system in our society and warrant discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets, or at least idealized free markets, manifest disorganized decentralization in that they can be thought of as a system of warring states, each state a good or service or product or idea competing to achieve market dominance. As I explain in this blog post, warring states are prime examples of disorganized decentralization and often lead to disorganized centralization when a clear winner emerges. So too with markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gutenberg press: Organized Decentralization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gutenberg Press decentralized the power over knowledge by allowing for the accelerated distribution of previously handwritten-only texts. In Europe, the technology allowed for the decentralization of knowledge away from the aristocracy and the church.  The organized nature appears within this new publishing industry, where a group of people with the resources to do so willingly decided to increase the distribution of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet: Organized Decentralization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The precursor to cryptocurrency and the underlying technology that powers it, the internet, and its organized, decentralized nature, inspired cryptocurrency and enabled its creation. What the internet decentralizes is computing power. Sort of self evidently, like the Turing Machines that power it, the internet is an &lt;em&gt;organized&lt;/em&gt; network of computers that gives its users the power to decentralize anything that can be algorithmically encoded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence: Organized Centralization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or at least this is where it generally stands with regards to the state of AI today, April 2021, which pretty much just means Machine Learning. I’m not really taking into account Artificial General Intelligence at all, since it doesn’t exist (yet). As AI technology has advanced, we have increasingly and willingly handed the power to control aspects of our lives to these machines. AI is now starting to drive for us. AI controls our media feeds on social media. AI controls our informational feeds on search engines. AI controls many of the investment decisions made by large investment groups. It has permeated all of society, so far with our consent. Although, as it starts being used for applications like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2018/2/27/17054740/palantir-predictive-policing-tool-new-orleans-nopd&quot;&gt;authoritarian&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnet.com/news/in-china-facial-recognition-public-shaming-and-control-go-hand-in-hand/&quot;&gt;surveillance&lt;/a&gt;, its position on the axis begins to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that perhaps the technology itself is just a tool and should not be the basis of analysis. Instead, the system using the technology to advance its needs should be what is placed on the axes. For example with authoritarian AI: the U.S. or Chinese governmental systems. Which means this whole post should maybe be about decentralized finance instead of cryptocurrency, but alas, it is written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thanks&lt;/strong&gt; to Ross Hardin, Ryan Wells, Robert Dominguez &lt;!--&lt;span class=&quot;hide&quot;&gt;(Praise be to He, The Dark Lord)&lt;/span&gt;--&gt;, and Hannah Gooden for reading drafts of this and helping me stress test the ideas.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alejandro Londono</name></author><category term="cryptocurrency" /><category term="blogposts" /><summary type="html">Bitcoin and cryptocurrency will replace fiat currency as the dominant form of transactional capital on the planet.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Take Aways from ‘My Stroke of Insight’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reading/blogposts/2021/02/15/my-stroke-of-insight.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Take Aways from ‘My Stroke of Insight’" /><published>2021-02-15T04:30:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-15T04:30:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reading/blogposts/2021/02/15/my-stroke-of-insight</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reading/blogposts/2021/02/15/my-stroke-of-insight.html">&lt;!-- ## Take Aways and Reflections From &apos;My Stroke of Insight&apos; by Dr. Jill Bolte Taylor, Ph. D. --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I tasked myself with the New Year’s Resolution of &lt;a href=&quot;http://reading.alondono.me&quot;&gt;reading one book a week&lt;/a&gt;. Throughout the year I plan on making intermittent blog posts exploring my take aways from some of the books that make a strong impression on me. The week of January 31, 2021 I read ‘My Stroke of Insight’ by &lt;a href=&quot;http://drjilltaylor.com/&quot;&gt;Dr. Jill Bolte Taylor&lt;/a&gt;, Ph. D, a Harvard trained neuroscientist. This book details Dr. Taylor’s observations regarding her stroke experience and the recovery that followed. She briefly touches on topics of neuroscience followed by deeper insights into her gained understanding of stroke recovery, overall well being, and happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always had an underlying interest and curiosity for neuroscience. In college I began a neuroscience minor before deciding neuro fit my interests better as a side hobby and switching to math. However, this curiosity never disappeared, and it drew me to the unique perspective offered by Dr. Taylor’s neuroscientific recounting of her stroke. After finishing this book, I can not recommend it enough as an avenue for self reflection, gratitude, and inspiration. Here I outline some of my key take aways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;general-bio-and-neuro-fun-facts&quot;&gt;General Bio and Neuro Fun(?) Facts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of the book is narrative in fashion, but the opening two chapters introduce the reader to a quick, layman friendly, technical explanation of the neuroanatomy and neuro-mechanisms underlying strokes. I want to share some interesting facts I learned about the different ways strokes manifest, and why they happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that blood is toxic to neurons if it comes in direct contact with them? I did not. If a vein ruptures in the brain and blood spills out, the blood kills any neurons it touches. This is why aneurysms (caused by the rupturing a blood vessel) and other hemorrhagic strokes can be so crippling and often deadly. Terrifying… but also fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these chapters Dr. Taylor explains how the majority of strokes occur due to blood clots cutting off the oxygen supply to the brain and causing the traumatization and death of neurons. She goes on to elaborate on how a smaller minority of strokes can also take place due to the rupturing of a blood vessel or vein spilling blood into the brain, and, again, killing neurons (which is what happened to her).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Not quite so) fun facts!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;computational-language-in-the-biological-sciences&quot;&gt;Computational Language in the Biological Sciences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As information processing machines, our ability to process data about the external world begins at the level of sensory perception. pg. 18&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My computer science education lacked coverage of Biology. This is expected as the overlap between these two fields is one that must be actively sought out. I have however, ventured into the subject, on occasion, in my extra-curricular reading. I’ve read two other bio-centric books&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#footnoteone&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in the last 3 or so years, and between those and this one, I find myself intrigued by how often &lt;em&gt;computational&lt;/em&gt; style language shows up in biological writing. For example, when these texts focus on the subject of genetics, words such as &lt;em&gt;code&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;encoding&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;program&lt;/em&gt; appear liberally. Similarly, when Dr. Taylor writes about the brain, she infuses the words &lt;em&gt;machines&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;code&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;pixels&lt;/em&gt; throughout her descriptions of its operations and information processing. Examples of this can be seen in this section’s opening quote as well as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our visual field … is divided into billions of tiny spots or pixels.
…this information is eventually coded as different colors by the visual cortex in the occipital region of our brain. pg. 19&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of language makes sense to use as this is both literally and analogously what is happening biologically. With regards to genetics, chromosomes are, quite literally, a physical code for protein synthesis, and in neuroscience the human brain is indeed actively translating electro-chemical encodings into practical information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to me this also brings to mind questions of how and why computation embeds itself so deeply in the natural world. Recursion, a tool computer scientists are deeply acquainted with, appears again in genetic replication as well as more macroscopically in fractal formations like vegetation and coastlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the idea of computation a human creation? Or is it, in fact, an emergent property of nature? Similar questions arise in physics and quantum computing. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://quantum.country/qcvc&quot;&gt;Quantum computing for the very curious&lt;/a&gt;, Michael Nielsen, expanding on David Deutsch’s original pondering over the physical nature of computation, states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… computers aren’t just human inventions. They are a fundamental feature of the universe, the answer to a simple and profound question about how the universe works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does the naturally emergent truly end and the man made begin? These lines that differentiate supposedly separate fields begin to blur when exploring these fields in conjunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;language-akin-to-that-of-meditation&quot;&gt;Language Akin to that of Meditation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the book, the similarities between how Dr. Taylor spoke of her personality and mindset changes following her stroke and how experienced meditation practitioners speak about mindfulness and meditation stood out to me particularly. For example, Dr. Taylor throughout the text speaks about continuously finding ways to be present in the moment. She describes how when her mind starts drifting to subjects of the future or of the past or of distress she simply brings her focus back to the present moment and lets those thoughts pass her by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Caught in the loop of deep grief, my chest tightens, my breathing becomes shallow, and emotionally I feel depressed. … These passionate thoughts and feelings have the potential to jump instantly into my mind, but again, … I have the power to consciously choose which emotional and physiological loops I want to hook into. pg. 163&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The feeling of peace is something that happens in the present moment. It’s not something that we bring with us from the past or project into the future. Pg. 168&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This parallels closely the ideas of presence and detachment that arise in meditation and mindfulness. We can see the in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mindful.org/how-to-meditate-3/&quot;&gt;How to Meditate&lt;/a&gt; , where mindful.org states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When we pay attention to our breath, we are learning how to return to, and remain in, the present moment—to anchor ourselves in the here and now on purpose, without judgement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, this article goes on to elaborate on some of the key behaviors that underly mindfulness practice and how they bring about an ability to choose one’s focus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We “practice” mindfulness so we can learn how to recognize when our minds are doing their normal everyday acrobatics, and maybe take a pause from that for just a little while so we can choose what we’d like to focus on.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mindful.org/how-to-meditate-3/&quot;&gt;How to Meditate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This resonates with the way Dr. Taylor described her ability to become abstractly aware of her emotions and “choose” what feelings to hook into and which feelings to let go of. Much like the earlier quote, she again states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I learned that I had the power to choose whether to hook into a feeling and prolong its presence in my body, or just let it quickly flow right out of me. Pg. 126&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Taylor uses her experience to encourage the reader to engage with the present more often and be more introspective towards the state of their mind and body. The philosophy and behaviors that Dr. Taylor advocates for are not necessarily &lt;em&gt;identical&lt;/em&gt; to those encouraged by mindfulness proponents, but they are in many ways similar and seek to produce the same results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am by no means a highly experienced practitioner of mindfulness, but I have, at times, engaged in periods of consistent daily meditation that produced a heightened sense of awareness over the thoughts and emotions that arose in my mind and body. Anecdotally, I can concur that this awareness gave rise to a nuanced understanding of choice over how to react to those feelings, and at times even allowed for the embracing or releasing of them at will. Remnants of this awareness have continued existing in my conscious psyche, but not as vividly without extended periods of consistent meditation practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More comparisons between mindfulness teachings and Dr. Taylor’s insights continue throughout the book. A common description of meditation involves imagining your thoughts as clouds floating in the wind. As they come into your mind, you &lt;em&gt;acknowledge&lt;/em&gt; their presence, but you do not hold on to them, you simply let them drift away with the breeze. Similarly, Dr. Taylor states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Become aware of your extraneous thoughts, thank them for their service, and ask them to be silent for a little while. Pg. 170&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this same way, Dr. Taylor alludes to a certain detachment from thoughts and emotions while still acknowledging them so as to allow for a choice in their engagement, just as mindfulness does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, guided meditations, a popular introductory avenue into the mindfulness practice, often instruct the participant to place their focus on their senses. To focus on how their breath feels flowing in and out of their lungs. How their body feels against the ground or chair they are sitting on. What kind of sounds or smells they notice around them. If a thought comes in, they are told not to reject it, but to also not embrace it. Again, it is meant to be but a cloud drifting through the wind. They let it go, and return the attention to the senses or a mantra or the counting of their breaths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Taylor speaks of how she engages in this same kind of behavior:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To help me find my way back into my peaceful right mind, … I find that paying attention to sensory information as it streams into my body is a very helpful tool. Pg 171&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She elaborates on this by speaking about her focus on the breath and the body and how she relates that back to the present moment, much like mindfulness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you will, think about your breathing. … What is going on inside your body? Is it in a comfortable position? … Take another deep breath, and now another. Relax into your body … Revel in the fact that in this moment, you are a living, thriving human being! Pg. 171&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parallels to mindfulness can again be seen in its meditation practices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Try this: feel your feet on the ground right now. In your shoes or without, it doesn’t matter. Then track or scan over your whole body, bit by bit—slowly—all the way up to the crown of your head. The point of this practice is to check in with your whole body… Only rules are: No judging, no wondering, no worrying (all activities your mind may want to do); just check in with the physical feeling of being in your body. Aches and pains are fine. You don’t have to do anything about anything here. You’re just noticing.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mindful.org/how-to-meditate-3/&quot;&gt;How to Meditate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These key insights from Dr. Taylor’s experience resonate throughout the book, and she places significant emphasis on them. However, Dr. Taylor never mentions meditation or mindfulness or makes any direct connection to it, and many tenets that constitute mindfulness practice are missing from her narrative. Regardless, it is widely agreed that there is no one “correct” way to engage in meditation, it is instead an umbrella term that encapsulates many different disciplines, mindfulness among them, and I would go as far as claiming that if one subscribes to the ideas and behaviors that Dr. Taylor advocates for, the subsequent actions and results fall under said umbrella.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;concluding-thoughts&quot;&gt;Concluding Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know exactly what I hope to achieve with this or any future blog posts. The format is not exactly conventional. It feels very much like it exists in an in-between-state, not quite an essay, but also rather long when compared to traditional blog posts. Something of an organized post-stream of consciousness. Anyhow, it is of value to me to organize my post-reading thoughts in this way, and I hope that as a reader you may derive some value from it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With regards to ‘My Stroke of Insight’, it is not a terribly long read (roughly 196 pages), and if you feel compelled to read it after having read this post, I hope you find that there is even more value to be extracted from its pages than just what I have detailed here. Dr. Taylor’s resilience, determination, and success in recovering from her stroke after having lost the majority of her faculties inspired me to be a happier, more appreciative person, and hopefully it can do so for you as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;footnoteone&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;. The two other bio books I have read recently are The Gene by Siddhartha Mukherjee and The Language of God by Francis Collins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thanks&lt;/strong&gt; to Ryan Wells, Hannah Gooden, and Ross Hardin for reading drafts of this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alejandro Londono</name></author><category term="reading" /><category term="blogposts" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/welcome/2021/02/14/welcome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome" /><published>2021-02-14T16:30:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-14T16:30:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/welcome/2021/02/14/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/welcome/2021/02/14/welcome.html">&lt;p&gt;Hi and welcome to my blog. Here I hope to write about things that are on my mind that don’t require a formal essay. Please enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alejandro Londono</name></author><category term="welcome" /><summary type="html">Hi and welcome to my blog. Here I hope to write about things that are on my mind that don’t require a formal essay. Please enjoy.</summary></entry></feed>